Haldeman, Mrs. S. A. mss., 1839-1953 LMC 1447
Lilly Library
Haldeman, Mrs. S. A. mss.
1839-1953
Lilly Library
LMC 1447
8 Boxes 8 standard
1 folio oversize
The Haldeman, Mrs. S. A., mss., 1839-1953, consists mainly of personal correspondence and papers of banker Sarah Alice (Addams) Haldeman, 1853-1915.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchase: 1961, 1963, 1964, 1965
Biographical Note
Sarah Alice (Addams) Haldeman, (Mrs. Henry Winfield Haldeman), 1853-1915, was a banker. Her daughter was Anna Marcet (Haldeman) Haldeman-Julius, 1887-1941, author, editor, actress, feminist, and bank president.
Sarah Alice (Addams) Haldeman was born on 5 June 1854 in Cedarville, Illinois, to John Huy and Sarah (Weber) Addams. She married physician and banker Henry Winfield Haldeman, 1848-1905, on 25 October 1875; their daughter Anna Marcet was born on 18 June 1887. In the 1890s, Haldeman was the president of the Girard (Kansas) Board of Education. Also in the 1890s and into the 1900s, she was active in church work and women's clubs, and on 21 January 1899 she was elected the first president of the Girard Public Library Association. At the death of her husband in 1905, she succeeded him as president of the State Bank of Girard, and was elected vice-president for the Third District of the Kansas State Bankers Association. Haldeman died on 19 March 1915 at Augustana Hospital, Chicago, and is buried in Cedarville, Iowa.
Anna Marcet (Haldeman) Haldeman-Julius was born to Sarah Alice (Addams) Haldeman and Henry Winfield Haldeman on 18 June 1887 in Girard, Kansas. She studied at Rockford Seminary, Rockford, Illinois, 1902-1903; Dearborn Seminary, Chicago, Illinois, 1904-1905; Bryn Mawr College, 1905-1908; and the American Academy of Dramatic Arts, New York, 1908-1910. From 1910 to 1913, she acted in stock companies in the United States and Canada under the name Jean Marcet. Haldeman-Julius served as vice-president of the State Bank of Girard, Kansas from 1915 to 1925, and officer of the Kansas State Bankers Association from 1915 to 1917. In 1916, she married editor Emanuel Julius, 1889-1951, who adopted her last named in hyphenate, and the two established the Haldeman-Julius publishing house in Girard, Kansas. Between 1916 and 1931, she published several books, and in 1931, she travelled to Russia and collected funds due her and her husband from sale of translations of their works. She died on 13 February 1941.
Arrangement
The contents of this collection are arranged into five series: I. Correspondence; II. Miscellaneous; III. Writings; IV. Printed Material; V. Photographs & Negatives.
Scope and Contents
The Haldeman, Mrs. S. A., mss., 1839-1953, consists mainly of personal correspondence and papers of banker Sarah Alice (Addams) Haldeman, 1853-1915.
The first box in the collection contains a folder of biographical and genealogical material on the family.
The bulk of the material in the collection is family correspondence, primarily letters to Mrs. Haldeman, from her daughter, Anna Marcet Haldeman, while a student at Rockford Seminary, Dearborn Seminary, Bryn Mawr College, and the American Academy of Dramatic Arts; on a trip to Europe in the summer of 1908; and as an actress; and letters, 1870-1915, to Mrs. Haldeman from her sister, Jane Addams, 1860-1935, director of Hull House, Chicago, Ill. Included are papers, 1885-1913, relating to church work and the Women's Federation of Clubs in Kansas; some correspondence and papers of Martha Addams, and a sister of Mrs. Haldeman and Jane Addams who died at the age of 16; and some correspondence and papers, 1839-1888, of the Weber family of which Mrs. Sarah (Weber) Addams, mother of Mrs. Haldeman and Jane, was a member.
The material after the death of Mrs. Haldeman consists primarily of letters, 1916-1925, from Jane Addams to her niece, Mrs. Anna Marcet (Haldeman) Haldeman-Julius, correspondence of Mrs. Anna Marcet (Haldeman) Haldeman-Julius as secretary of the Kansas state bankers association, 1915- 1917; letters pertaining to her trip to Russia in 1931; 1918 correspondence of her husband, Emanuel Haldeman-Julius in his effort to keep out of the service in World War I; and correspondence with her children, Alice and Henry.
Among the correspondents represented in the collection are: Mrs. Anna (Hostetter) Addams, Jane Addams, John Huy Addams, Mrs. Sarah (Weber) Addams, Henry Justin Allen, Philip Pitt Campbell, Arthur Capper, Charles Curtis, Frederick Eugene Farnsworth, George Haldeman, Henry Winfield Haldeman, Mrs. Sarah Alice (Addams) Haldeman, Mrs. Anna Marcet (Haldeman) Haldeman-Julius) Emanuel Haldeman-Julius, Mrs. Josephine Conger Kaneko, Julia Clifford Lathrop, Lorenzo D. Lewelling, L. A. Libel, Mary Catherine (Addams) Linn, John Alexander Logan, James Hubert McVicker, Mrs. Elizabeth (Weber) Reiff, Mary Shaw, Jouett Shouse, Upton Beall Sinclair, T. J. Sweeney, Joseph Taggart, George Weber, Jr.
Included in the collection are undated typewritten mss. of Sir Richard Burton's "The Sotadic Zone," edited by A. F. Niemoeller; Hereward Carrington's "Electricity and Life: Physics and Gravitation"; Jules Guyot's "Breviary of Experimental Love," translated by A. F. Niemoeller; Joseph McCabe's "Baron d'Holbach and His Age," "Judged," and "The Sentimental Religion of Rousseau"; Clinton A. Sanders' "[Dictionary of Slang of the Army, Navy, and Marines in World Wars I and II]"; Natalie Schretter's "I Remember Clarence Darrow"; George H. Shoaf's "Fighting for Freedom"; Anna Marcet and Emanuel Haldeman-Julius' "Violence," "The Singing Flower," and "The Pool" in the hand of Mrs. Anna Marcet Haldeman-Julius; and anonymous typewritten manuscript entitled "The Bomb Is Planted," "The Mistress of the Many Windows," "The Art of Preserving One's Manhood," "Caterpillar and Butterfly," "The Sage," and "Shadows."
The collection contains a few photographs of members of the family and friends, and of the Haldeman-Julius company's building, workrooms, and employees.
Printed material in the collection consists principally of newspaper clippings, etc. relating to banking, and theater programs and newspaper clippings relating to the theater, particularly to Jean Marcet's performances.
Note on Indexing Term - "World War, 1914-1918": Included is 1918 correspondence of Emanuel Haldeman-Julius which details his effort to keep out of the service in World War I. Also included is a copy of Clinton A. Sanders' "Dictionary of Slang of the Army, Navy and Marines in World Wars I and II."
Related Materials
See Haldeman mss., Haldeman mss. II, & Haldeman mss. III, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Theater; Women; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945; Sisters--United States; Families--United States--History--20th century; Addams, Jane, 1860-1935; Haldeman, Sarah Alice, 1853-1915; Haldeman-Julius, Alice; Haldeman-Julius, E. (Emanuel), 1889-1951; Haldeman-Julius, Henry; Haldeman-Julius, Marcet, 1887-1941
- I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - 1839-1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1908 (Box 2)
  - 1909-1910, Sept. (Box 3)
  - 1910, Oct. - 1913, Mar. (Box 4)
  - 1913, Apr. - 1916 (Box 5)
  - 1917-1953 (Box 6)
- II. MISCELLANEOUS (Box 6)
- III. WRITINGS (Box 6)
- IV. PRINTED MATERIALS
  - 1910-1918 (Box 7)
  - The Art of Preserving One's Manhood (Ovflat 1)
- V. PHOTOGRAPHS & NEGATIVES
  - Photographs (Box 8)
  - Negatives